{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>In this campaign\u2019s first battle, Admiral Crutchley was defeated at Savo Island</em>. Edson\u2019s rangers successfully defended the Lunga ridge during this campaign, which was codenamed Operation Watchtower. Supplies were transported down \u201cthe Slot\u201d to this battle by the Tokyo express, and the Cactus Air Force protected the winners of this campaign. Successful defenses of Henderson Field were vital to its outcome. For the point, name this 1942 campaign over a namesake southern Solomon Island, which along with Midway, is considered a turning point of World War II's Pacific theater.", "answer": "<b><u>Guadalcanal</u></b> campaign [accept Operation <b><u>Watchtower</u></b> until \u201cWatchtower\u201d is read]  {II}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>A king of this name was defeated by the Kalbid emir of Sicily at the Battle of Stilo.</em> Writers like Widukind of Corvey and Hroswitha of Gandersheim were patronized by kings of this name during their namesake renaissance. A king of this name married Adelaide of Italy, signed a \"Diploma\" with Pope John XII, and defeated the chieftains Lel and Sur near Augsburg. That king with this name was the son of Henry the Fowler and defeated the Magyars at the Battle of Lechfeld (<b>pr. LECK-feld</b>). For the point, give this name of the first Germanic Holy Roman Emperor.", "answer": "<b><u>Otto</u></b> [or <b><u>Otto</u></b> I; or <b><u>Otto</u></b> II]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>This college program missed a chance to recruit Magic Johnson because Coach Larry Farmer</em> <em>wanted Albert King instead</em>. This team lost to an Elvin Hayes led Houston squad in the \"Game of the Century,\" the first regular season NCAA game broadcast in prime-time. Under the \"Wizard of Westwood,\" this program had such great players as Bill Walton and Kareem Abdul-Jabbar. For the point, name this college basketball team, which under coach John Wooden won 88 straight games in the 1970's.", "answer": "<b><u>UCLA</u> </b>Bruins [ or <b><u>Bruins</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>While in one of these places, Richard of Wallingford built an intricate astronomical clock.</em> The Plan of St. Gall is a drawing of one of these places. Alcuin (<b>pr. AL-koo-in</b>) of York sent a letter to Higbald following the destruction of one of these places by Vikings. Columba founded one of these institutions on the Isle of Kells, and they were the subject of the Cluniac reforms. Robert Aske led the Pilgrimage of Grace in response to the dissolution of these institutions. For the point, name these institutions exemplified by Lindisfarne, where monks lived.", "answer": "<b><u>monasterie</u></b>s [or <b><u>abbey</u></b>s]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>This man joked that Ambassador Bryce Mackasey was a prostitute</em>. This leader sent troops in Operation Friction in 1991, the first time since 1974 that his country engaged in direct combat operations. With his wife and an American couple, he was televised singing \"When Irish Eyes are Smiling\" on Saint Patrick's Day. This man was criticized for \"sucking up\" at the Shamrock Summit to his ally, Ronald Reagan. He was succeeded in his highest office by Kim Campbell. For the point, name this Progressive Conservative Canadian Prime Minister from 1984 to 1993.", "answer": "Brian <b><u>Mulroney</u></b> (\"muhl-ROO-nee\")  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This belief system is said to seek \"the aestheticization of politics\" in a Walter Benjamin essay</em> <em>about the \"work of art\".</em> The most recent draining of the Pontine Marshes was undertaken by a leader of this philosophy. The Battle for Land and Battle for Births were programs set up as part of this ideology, which many Futurist artists later subscribed to after the peak of their careers. This ideology took its name from an object carried by lictors in ancient Rome, consisting largely of a bundle of tied sticks representing strength in numbers. For the point, name this authoritarian ideology of the Black Shirts in 1920s Italy.", "answer": "<b><u>fascism</u></b> [or <b><u>fascist</u></b>s]  {II}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>Metellus Scipio commanded the center for the losing side in this battle, with Lucius Domitius</em> <em>Ahenobarbus on his left.</em> The losing commander of this battle was killed under the advice of Pothinus. It was fought along the bank of the Enipeus river. The winner of this battle used a fourth line of troops, thrusting with their pila to counter the opponent\u2019s superior cavalry, which was led by his former lieutenant, Titus Labienus. This battle was preceded by the Battle of Dyrrhachium. For the point, name this battle in which Julius Caesar decisively defeated the Optimates (<b>pr. OP-tee-MAH-tace</b>) forces of Pompey the Great.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Pharsalus</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>This was the highest post held by a man whose 2003 speech on direct democracy was</em> <em>sponsored by the Holocaust denying Barnes Review journal</em>. A man in this post published a portion of the Pentagon Papers he read into the Congressional Record in 1971. A more recent man to hold it would have become the first convicted felon to win re-election to the Senate, but lost that election and died in a plane crash two years later. This post was held by Mike Gravel and the Senator who served as a Republican longer than anyone in history. For the point, name this position held for over 40 years by Ted Stevens.", "answer": "<b><u>Senator</u></b> from <b><u>Alaska</u></b> [\u201cSenator\u201d is not needed after \u201cSenate\u201d is read, otherwise, prompt on \u201cSenator\u201d]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>According to its author, the groundwork for this book was laid out with the publication of an</em> <em>anonymous work on natural history calledVestiges</em>. This work\u2019s sixth edition inserted a chapter refuting the criticisms of George Mivart. The ideas of this text were called a \u201cUniversal Acid\u201d by Daniel Dennett. For this book\u2019s fifth edition, the author modified it to include a phrase that was first used by Herbert Spencer. Its full title describes the \u201cmeans of natural selection\u201d and the \u201cpreservation of favored races in the struggle for life.\u201d For the point, name this book by Darwin.", "answer": "<em>On the</em> <em><b><u>Origin of Species</u></b></em>  {II}", "metadata": "Ike"}, {"question": "<em>This region shares its name with the class of World War I battleships that improved on the</em> Courbet<em> class.</em> This region is the home of a savory pastry called the galette. A war of succession fought over a duchy in this region led to the death of John of Montfort. Some women in this region wear a traditional tall cap called a \u201cbigouden,\u201d which is made from its famous lace. The namesake ethnic group of this region traces its origins to Celtic tribes which crossed the English channel heading south. For the point, name this western region of France.", "answer": "<b><u>Brittany</u></b> [or <b><u>Bretagne</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "EA"}, {"question": "<em>A worker in this state was convicted of a crime thanks to testimony from his girlfriend Twila</em> <em>Hoffman</em>. In this state, a mentally challenged woman known as Patricia McGee was sexually assaulted. The perpetrator of that crime in this state was stabbed to death there in a bar argument in 1976 and had previously made money giving autographs to police officers. The conviction of a man who kidnapped and raped a woman in this state was vacated because he was not told of his right to remain silent. For the point, name this state where Ernesto Miranda was arrested.", "answer": "<b><u>Arizona</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>One of these structures was billed as the \"Hero Project of the Century\" and was called the</em> <em>BAM.</em> During their revolt, the Czechoslovak legion captured one of these structures. The theories of Friedrich List inspired Sergei Witte's plan for the construction of one of these structures. Lenin travelled along one of these structures in a \"sealed\" chamber during his return from exile in Switzerland. For the point, name these structures, examples of which include the Trans-Siberian one.", "answer": "Russian <b><u>railway</u></b>s [or <b><u>railroad</u></b>s; accept <b><u>train</u></b>s until \"legion\" is read]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>This ruler commissioned a journey that would bring back live myrrh trees to grow in Egypt</em> <em>for the first time.</em> The large Unfinished Obelisk, found in a stone quarry in Aswan, dates back to the reign of this pharaoh. This ruler sponsored an expedition which met the plump Queen of Punt. This ruler ordered the construction of the Djeser-Djeseru, a temple in the Deir al-Bahdi complex. This leader during the Eighteenth Dynasty ruled as regent for her stepson. For the point, name this female pharaoh.", "answer": "<b><u>Hatshepsut</u> </b> {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>In this novel, one character obtains arrows by sending out dummies in boats, and then</em> <em>collecting the arrows shot at the dummies.</em> A character in this novel is given the horse Red Hare from his foster father. This work describes a corrupt set of eunuchs as well as the Yellow Turban Rebellion. Liu Bei, Guan Yu, and Zhang Fei become sworn brothers in this novel, which features the manipulative Cao Cao. For the point, name this work, which along with <em>Journey to the West</em>, <em>Water Margin</em>, and <em>The Dream of the Red Chamber</em>, is one of the four classical novels of China.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Romance of the Three Kingdoms</u></b></em> [or <b><u>sanguo</u></b> yanyi]  {II}", "metadata": "Ike"}, {"question": "<em>The house that this man built during his ambassadorship to the Netherlands became the first</em> <em>American embassy on foreign soil.</em> This man anonymously denounced the Stamp Act with his article series \u201cA Dissertation on the Canon and Feudal Law.\u201d He quipped that \u201cFacts are stubborn things\u201d to justify his legal defense of the redcoats who perpetrated the Boston Massacre. The Kentucky and Virginia Resolves were drafted as a response to the unpopular Alien and Sedition Acts passed during this man\u2019s presidency. For the point, name this husband of the enlightened woman Abigail, the second president of the US.", "answer": "John <b><u>Adams</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "<em>It\u2019s not David (<b>pr. dah-VEED</b>), but a large black cloud dominates the sky in one of this</em> <em>artist's paintings, which depicts Hannibal crossing the Alps.</em> After witnessing the event, this artist created two paintings of The Burning of the Houses of Lords and Commons, which differ in perspective<em>.</em> One of his paintings was displayed with lines from the poem <em>Ye Marines of</em> <em>England</em>, which state \"The flag which braved the battle and the breeze no longer owns her.\" This painter showed a steamboat pulling a ship-of-the-line in <em>The Fighting Temeraire</em>. For the point, what Romantic painter depicted a train in <em>Rain, Steam, and Speed</em>?", "answer": "Joseph Mallord William <b><u>Turner</u></b> [or J.M.W. <b><u>Turner</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>One company in this industry put a double-headed eagle on the extra-wide white stripe in its</em> <em>flag</em>. St. Louis, Missouri was founded by the Chouteau family that became wealthy through this industry. Members of this industry participated in the Rocky Mountain Rendezvous. This industry traded point blankets for their namesake product. John Jacob Astor founded an American company in this industry that lost their competition for market share with the Canadian Hudson\u2019s Bay Company. For the point, name this industry dealing in animal pelts.", "answer": "<b><u>Fur</u></b> trade [prompt on <b><u>trap</u></b>ping]  {II}", "metadata": "PL"}, {"question": "<em>A section in this man's magnum opus on the \"world-historicality\" of individuals might have</em> <em>been inspired by Ernst Junger's war memoir \u201cStorm and Steel</em>.\u201dThis thinker, who claimed that all philosophers between Plato and himself misunderstood the \"ontological question,\" was revealed in 2014 to have kept \"black notebooks\" containing anti-Semitic rants. This teacher and lover of Hannah Arendt dismissed his mentor Edmund Husserl after being appointed rector of the University of Freiburg in 1933. For the point, name this German philosopher who remained unrepentant about his Nazi party membership, the author of <em>Being and Time</em>.", "answer": "Martin <b><u>Heidegger</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>In 1988, this politician led efforts to oust Jim Wright as Speaker of the House.</em> This man expressed annoyance at supposedly being asked to exit from the rear of Air Force One following a flight to the funeral of Yitzhak Rabin, which allegedly led him to force the 1995-1996 government shutdown. This man resigned from his highest post after the Republicans lost seats in the 1998 elections during the Lewinsky scandal. For the point, name this speaker of the House who led the Republican victory of 1994 and crafted the <em>Contract With America</em>.", "answer": "Newton \u201cNewt\u201d <b><u>Gingrich</u></b> [or Newton <b><u>McPherson</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "ED"}, {"question": "<em>This king's daughter brought a sacred sapling to the court of King Tissa.</em> This ruler supposedly operated a torture chamber inside a beautiful palace known as his \"hell.\" The Barabar caves were hewn out of granite during this leader's rule. This king's son Mahinda was a monk who travelled to Sri Lanka, and this king was disturbed by the bloodiness of the Kalinga War. A statue of four lions once stood on a pillar erected by this king, who also ordered the creation of many Rock edicts. For the point, name this Buddhist convert and ruler of the Mauryan Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Ashoka</u></b> Maurya  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>This group successfully defended a siege of Bremen and won the proceeding Battle of</em> <em>Drakenburg.</em> The defeat of this group led to the Capitulation of Wittenberg. This group fell apart after suffering a defeat at the Battle of Muhlberg. Taking its name from a town in Thuringia, this group was first formed by Philip I of Hesse and John Frederick I of Saxony. For the point, what league of German states entered a namesake war fighting against Charles V to protect Protestantism?", "answer": "<b><u>Schmalkaldic</u></b> League  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>This man led an expedition up the Orinoco River, which he described in his book The</em> <em>Discoverie of Guiana.</em> This man wrote a <em>Historie of the World</em>, with \"Historie\" spelled ending \"I-E,\" while imprisoned.After returning from a second expedition to find El Dorado, this man was executed for plotting to overthrow James I. His favor in the royal court soured following his marriage to Elizabeth Throckmorton. For the point, name this British explorer who sponsored the settlement of the Lost Colony of Roanoke in the state whose capital bears his name.", "answer": "Sir Walter <b><u>Raleigh</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "ED"}, {"question": "<em>This man was able to conquer one castle after flooding it by diverting a river</em>. He defeated Akechi Mitsuhide (<b>pr. mitt-sue-HEE-day</b>) at the Battle of Yamazaki, and started the construction of Osaka Castle. Due to his peasant birth, he took the title of regent rather than shogun. Towards the end of his life, this man tried to conquer China, but failed in his invasions of Korea. He set up a Council of Five Regents to allow his son to inherit power, which failed when Tokugawa Ieyasu took over as shogun. For the point, which second of the Three Unifiers of Japan after Oda Nobunaga helped end the Sengoku Period?", "answer": "<b><u>Toyotomi</u><u>Hideyoshi</u></b> [accept either]  {II}", "metadata": "TR"}, {"question": "<em>This organization carried out the</em> sermo generalis <em>ceremony</em>. This organization operated both <em>murus largus</em> and <em>murus strictus</em> prisons. One of these organizations was formally abolished by the regent Maria Cristina in 1834. The Portuguese incarnation of this organization carried out <em>auto-de-f\u00e9</em> ceremonies. Another of these organizations, which focused on <em>conversos</em> and was led by Tom\u00e1s de Torquemada, was set up by Ferdinand and Isabella of Spain. For the point, name these Catholic courts that investigated charges of heresy.", "answer": "<b><u>inquisition</u></b>s [accept <b><u>Roman Inquisition</u></b>, <b><u>Spanish Inquisition</u></b>, or <b><u>Portuguese</u></b> <b><u>Inquisition</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em>Before this battle, a Union attack forced M.L. Bonham to retreat to Centreville.</em> After this battle, the spy Rose Greenhow was arrested. This battle opened with Confederates under Nathan Evans defending the Warrenton Turnpike and Stone Bridge. At this battle, a rallying exhortation by Barnard Bee gave Stonewall Jackson his nickname. This battle ended when P.G.T. Beauregard\u2019s reinforced army forced Irvin McDowell to retreat. For the point, name this first major battle of the Civil War, fought near a Virginia rail junction.", "answer": "<b><u>First</u></b> Battle of <b><u>Bull Run</u></b> [or <b><u>First</u></b> Battle of <b><u>Manassas</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Bull Run</u></b> or <b><u>Manassas</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em>This scientist examined the rise and fall of the Assyrians and Persians in his occult treatise</em> <em>The Chronology of Ancient Kingdoms</em>. This natural philosopher included the section \u201cOn the System of the World\u201d in his magnum opus, whose title was borrowed by Alfred North Whitehead and Bertrand Russell for a later work. He once wrote in a letter to Robert Hooke that states \u201cif I have seen further, it is by standing on the shoulders of giants.\u201d For the point, name this author of the<em> Principia Mathematica</em> who supposedly derived his universal law of gravitation after an apple fell on his head.", "answer": "Isaac <b><u>Newton</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "Ike"}, {"question": "<em>The first of these wars featured trench warfare along the Chataldzha.</em> After that first of these wars, one participant\u2019s border was drawn between the ports of Enos and Midya. The second of these wars was ended by two treaties, Constantinople and Bucharest. In both of these wars, the city of Adrianople was contested. Albania declared independence during the first of these wars, whose peace negotiations in London were interrupted by the coup of the Young Turks. For the point, name these two conflicts named for a mountainous peninsula in southeast Europe.", "answer": "<b><u>Balkan</u></b> Wars [accept <b><u>First Balkan</u></b> War or <b><u>Second Balkan</u></b> War]  {II}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em>This piece\u2019s fourth movement opens with the so-called \u201cterror fanfare.\u201d</em> German POWs in World War I introduced the tradition of playing this piece in Japan on New Year\u2019s. Its third movement gives a prominent solo to the fourth horn player. The running length of a compact disc was supposedly increased to fit this work, and Johannes Brahms claimed \u201cany fool can see\u201d a similarity between this piece and his first symphony. Its final movement is the anthem of the European Union, and features lyrics from a Friedrich Schiller poem. For the point, what final Ludwig van Beethoven symphony ends with the \u201cOde to Joy\u201d?", "answer": "Ludwig van Beethoven\u2019s <b><u>Symphony #9</u></b> in D minor, opus 125 [or <b><u>\u201cChoral\u201d</u></b> <b><u>Symphony</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em>During a brief retirement, this man wrote a three-volume memoir that began with</em> The Call to Honor. This man was initially co-president of a provisional government before ousting Henri Giraud. He returned to his highest office after Ren\u00e9 Coty threatened to resign. The Secret Army Organization opposed this man, who was succeeded as president by Georges Pompidou. His tenure as president included his country\u2019s loss of Algeria and the mass unrest of May 1968. For the point, what father of the French Fifth Republic led Free French Forces during World War II?", "answer": "Charles Andr\u00e9 Joseph Marie <b><u>de Gaulle</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "Warning: Year and Country required. <em>One campaign ad during this election saw a candidate</em> <em>speak for three hours while a man behind him painted a mural.</em> In this election, the Joint List alliance marked the first time the four major parties of a minority ethnic group were united. Right before this election, the incumbent forged a recording of the leader of the Kulanu Party promising to support him and wrote a Facebook post warning that \u201cArab voters are coming out in droves\u201d. For the point, which recent election saw Likud Party receive the most votes under Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu?", "answer": "<b><u>2015 Israel</u></b>i legislative elections  {II}", "metadata": "TR"}, {"question": "<em>Two of these objects were used to save a Roman army from Commius and Vercassivellaunus.</em> These objects were made in the Cyclopean style in Mycenae (<b>pr. my-SEE-nay</b>) and Tiryns (<b>pr. TEER-inz</b>). A project of the emperor Aurelian was inspired by Servius Tullius\u2019 earlier use of these objects in Rome. At Alesia, Caesar used examples of these objects called contravallations and circumvallations. The Athenians accessed the port of Piraeus using \u201clong\u201d ones of these; a later Roman one extends from the River Tyne to Solway Firth. For the point, name these defensive structures exemplified by one named for Hadrian across Scotland.", "answer": "<b><u>wall</u></b>s [accept <b><u>dyke</u></b>s; accept <b><u>circumvallation</u></b> or <b><u>contravallation</u></b> before \u201cOffa\u201d]  {II}", "metadata": "SL"}, {"question": "<em>Fred Silverman hated this television program for referring to him as a \"lame-o.\"</em> In a controversial episode of this show a woman sang the song \"War\" and then ripped up a photo of Pope John Paul II. Dick Ebersol wanted to create this show to replace repeats of Johnny Carson's <em>Tonight Show</em>. This show's first cast was called the \"Not Ready for Prime-Time Players.\" Lorne Michaels created this show, which introduced such stars as Gilda Radner, John Belushi, and Chevy Chase. For the point, name this late-night comedy program that has aired for 40 years on NBC's weekend schedule.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Saturday Night Live</u></b></em> [or <em><b><u>SNL</u></b></em>; or <em><b><u>NBC\u2019s Saturday Night</u></b></em>]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>A general strike in this country followed the replacement of its \u201cConstructing Socialism\u201d</em> <em>movement with a \u201cNew Course.\u201d</em> This country\u2019s governing party was the SED. The secret police force of this country was led by Erich Mielke, and used a network of \u201cunofficial collaborators.\u201d Egon Krenz was the last general secretary of this country, whose other two general secretaries were Walter Ulbricht and Erich Honecker. The <em>Stasi</em> was the secret police of, for the point, what communist country that reunited with its western neighbor in 1989?", "answer": "<b><u>East Germany</u></b> [or <b><u>Ostdeutschland</u></b> or <b><u>German Democratic Republic</u></b> or <b><u>Deutsche</u></b> <b><u>Demokratische Republik</u></b> or <b><u>GDR</u></b> or <b><u>DDR</u></b>; do not accept nor prompt on <b><u>Germany</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em>An amended line in this treaty's Article IX said that certain citizens would now be \"admitted</em> <em>at the proper time\" instead of \"as soon as possible.\"</em> This treaty was negotiated by a former U.S. consul in Havana named Nicholas Trist, who ignored the President's attempts to recall him. Jefferson Davis proposed a failed amendment to this treaty which was opposed by Democratic leadership. The Wilmot Proviso banning slavery in the territory acquired failed to be added to this treaty. This treaty set the Rio Grande as a border for Texas. For the point, name this treaty that ended the Mexican-American War.", "answer": "Treaty of <b><u>Guadalupe Hidalgo</u></b> [or Treatyof <b><u>Peace, Friendship, Limits and</u></b> <b><u>Settlement between the United States of America and the Mexican Republic</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This man is praised as \"disdaining fortune, with his brandished steel.\"</em> This character is told that his face \"is as a book where men may read strange matters.\" Edward the Confessor sends troops behind the cover of uprooted trees against this thane. A play named for this man was written to honor James I, whose Stuart dynasty traced its lineage back to this man's friend Banquo. For the point, name this man who kills King Duncan to take over Scotland in a tragedy by Shakespeare.", "answer": "<b><u>Macbeth</u></b>  {II}  <b>Extra Tossup \u2013 ONLY READ IF A TOSSUP IS BOTCHED!</b>", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This politician\u2019s son died after developing an infected blister formed while playing tennis at</em> <em>the White House.</em> This President declined to visit the Gulf Coast after the Great Mississippi Flood and vetoed a federal farm relief bill proposed by Gilbert Haugen and Charles McNary. As Governor, he proclaimed there was \"no right to strike against the public safety\" when opposing a Boston policemen's strike. For the point, name this \"silent\" President who took office in 1923.", "answer": "(John) Calvin <b><u>Coolidge</u></b> Jr.  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}], "bonuses": []}